A Guide to the Virginia Ordnance Department Records, 1861-1864
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Ordnance Department Records, 1861-1864
Library of Virginia
38943
1.73 cubic feet (3 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Historical Information
The Ordnance Department was created by an act of the General Assembly on January 25, 1861. The department was to consist of a colonel of ordnance appointed by the governor and no more than six subordinate officers. Governor Letcher appointed Col. Charles Dimmock, former Commandant of the Public Guard and Superintendent of the Armory, as Colonel of Ordnance. On April 27, 1861, R.S. Garnett, Adjutant-General of the Virginia Forces, submitted General Order No. 3 which charged Dimmock with the duties of assembling and preparing ordnance for Virginia troops in field service. An ordinance was passed on May 1, 1861, placing the department under the control of the major general commanding the military and naval forces of Virginia. After the seizure of the United States Arsenal at Harper's Ferry by Virginia militia under Colonel Turner Ashby on April 18, 1861, all of the weapons, machinery, and stock were confiscated and transported to the Richmond Armory shortly thereafter. The armory was then leased to the Confederate government. The Ordnance Dept. took charge of repairing the armory and manufacturing arms for the war effort. On 15 May 1862, the General Assembly authorized the governor to commission John B. Floyd as a major general in the Virginia State Line. Two and a half million dollars was appropriated for Floyd's ten-thousand-man force. The Ordnance Dept. played an active role in arming Floyd's forces. Floyd's Army was later transferred to Confederate service on 28 February 1863. J.S. Shriver replaced Charles Dimmock as Colonel of Ordnance in October 1863 upon his death.
Scope and Content Information
These records relate to expenses incurred by the Ordnance Department between 1861 and 1864. Contains abstracts, vouchers, payrolls, correspondence, inspection certificates, and a report, all of which were submitted to the Auditing Board by Col. Charles Dimmock, Colonel of Ordnance, and later by Col. J.S. Shriver. The majority of this collection consists of abstracts and vouchers. The abstract provides a summary of all the vouchers submitted during a specific time. The vouchers acknowledge receipt of payment and were often numbered. The number on the abstract corresponds with the number of the voucher. Whenever an abstract exists for the vouchers, those vouchers are arranged in order by voucher number. There is a group of vouchers from 1861 and another from 1862, however, that were not abstracted. These vouchers are simply arranged in chronological order. The vouchers document a wide variety of expenses, but are mostly for weapons, ammunition, pay, transportation, and other sundry items. There is a large group of vouchers from Winchester for hauling the machinery at Harper's Ferry. There are also separate vouchers for Floyd's Army between May and December 1862.
Note that there are a few gaps in the records, most notably from January-February 1862, July & September-December 1863, and most of 1864. Some of these records can be found in the Records of the Auditing Board, 1861-1864. The payrolls relate to work done at the Richmond Armory reconstructing buildings, manufacturing arms, cleaning and repairing arms, fixing ammunition, etc. These payrolls provide the names of the workmen, how employed, length of employment, pay per day, total pay, and signatures. There are a few pieces of correspondence in the collection from Col. Dimmock to George W. Munford, President of the Auditing Board, and the Auditor of Public Accounts, and from Edward H. Fitzhugh, Examining Clerk, to the Auditing Board. Lastly, there is a report of the operations of the Ordnance Department submitted by Col. Shriver in April 1864.
Contents List
- Virginia Ordnance Department Records, 1861-1864
  - Abstract and Vouchers
    - 1861
      - Abstract A
        - Vouchers 1-48 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Voucher 49 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Abstract B - Vouchers 1-28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Abstract C - Vouchers 1-9 (Payrolls)(See Also Oversized) (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Abstract D - Vouchers 1-28 (See Also Oversized) (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Winchester
        - Vouchers 1-38, 1861 April-May (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Hauling Machinery (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Hauling Machinery (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1862
      - January-July (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - July-September
        - Abstract A - Vouchers 1-37 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Abstract B - Vouchers 1-7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - August-November (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - December (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Floyd's Army
        - 1862 May-June - Vouchers 1-28 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - 1862 July-September
          - Abstract A - Vouchers 1-84 (Box 2, Folder 2)
          - Abstract B - Vouchers 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 3)
          - Abstract C - Vouchers 1-3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - 1862 October-November - Vouchers 1-77 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - 1862 December - Vouchers 1-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1863
      - Abstract A
        - January - Vouchers 1-26 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - February - Vouchers 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - March - Vouchers 1-18 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - April - Vouchers 1-7 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - May - Vouchers 1-8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - June - Vouchers 1-16 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - August - Vouchers 1-18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Sept. - Vouchers 1-42 (See Also Oversized) (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Oct. - Vouchers 1-23 (See Also Oversized) (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Nov. (See Oversized) (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Dec. - Vouchers 1-6 (See Also Oversized) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1864
      - Jan. - Vouchers 1-5 (See Also Oversized) (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Feb. - Vouchers 1-7 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Jan.-July (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Inspection Certificates, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Report of Operations of the Ordnance Dept., 1864 (See Oversized) (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Oversized, 1861-1864
  - Abstract and Vouchers
    - 1861
      - Abstract C - Vouchers 1-8 - Payroll (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Abstract D - Vouchers 11 and 19 - Payroll of workmen engaged at pulling down and repairing the Armory (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Floyd's Army
      - Abstract A
        - 1862 May-June
          - Voucher 25 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 3)
          - Voucher 26 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - 1862 July-September
          - Voucher 36 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Voucher 37 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Voucher 66 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Voucher 67 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Voucher 82 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Voucher 83 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - 1862 October-November
          - Voucher 27 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 5)
          - Voucher 28 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 5)
          - Voucher 75 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 5)
          - Voucher 76 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - 1862 December
          - Voucher 29 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 6)
          - Voucher 30 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - 1863
          - January
            - Voucher 24 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 7)
            - Voucher 25 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 7)
          - February
            - Voucher 14 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 8)
            - Voucher 15 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 8)
          - March
            - Voucher 11 - Payroll of workmen engaged in storing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 9)
            - Voucher 16 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 9)
            - Voucher 17 - Payroll of workmen engaged in fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 9)
          - April
            - Voucher 7 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. (Box 3, Folder 10)
          - August
            - Voucher 18 - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1863
      - September
        - Abstract & Account Current (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - October
        - Abstract & Account Current (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - November
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - December
        - Abstract & Account Current (Box 3, Folder 15)
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1864
      - January
        - Account Current & Abstract of Expenditures made by Col. J.S. Shriver, January (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition, January (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - February
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition, January (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - March
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition, January (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - June
        - Payroll of workmen engaged in cleaning and repairing arms, etc. and fixing ammunition, January (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Report of the Operations of the Ordnance Dept., 1864 (Box 3, Folder 20)